what if there was something vital
missing in all our efforts to address
global challenges in the 21st century
what if it were simple to create and
what if all the pieces are ready to be
assembled now I'd like to share with you
my vision for a new field of science one
that combines the richness and rigor of
cognitive science with the expansive
efforts to formulate an integrative
understanding of the couple Earth's
system I'm calling this new field human
interface design for global change my
name is Joe brewer and I am on the path
to create this new field while pursuing
a PhD in the next few years I'll explain
what I mean by this in a moment first
let's start with a bit of context the
20th century was an era of
specialization many new fields of
research were created that separate one
domain of knowledge from another
interdepartmental and disciplinary silos
biology chemistry physics literature
history on and on researchers and
scholars separated from each other and
blind to what is happening in other
buildings and other halls across the
academic world the 21st century must be
an era of synthesis and integration the
challenges set before us are incredibly
complex unfolding as seamlessly
interconnected patterns that span the
globe it is time to bring what we know
together and build platforms for
holistic knowledge whose complexity
matches that of the real world for my
part I want to combine two overarching
themes cognitive science and its
application to global issues together
this provides a foundation for analyzing
the human dimension of Earth's systems
at universities across the globe the
study of atmosphere ocean and land is
beginning to melt into a single
framework new schools are being formed
that combine geology geography and
atmospheric science together I helped
design one of the first undergraduate
majors
in this new field almost a decade ago so
it's something I'm quite familiar with
combined with the study of living
systems vast ecosystems of plants
animals and fungi this overarching
synthesis is known as Earth System
science but something is missing humans
we are the largest driver of global
change in the world today and yet our
studies of the Earth's system do not
adequately represent the human dimension
or biological makeup or beliefs our
economic and political ideologies the
large-scale behaviors of what is proven
to be the most disruptive and impactful
species for natural systems on the
planet humanity stands at a crossroad
will we continue to deplete the world's
resources cripple the planets living
systems and drive ourselves to
extinction or will we build viable
models for urban development economic
progress and civic action that
transition us to long-term
sustainability and resilience the
absence of integrative methodologies for
applying cognitive science to the study
of earth systems takes away our capacity
to systematically analyze and design
innovative solutions to the world's
problems during a time of great
consequence we have to get the human
response right in order to survive as a
species time is of the essence and I am
just the person to take the lead with
formal training and Earth System science
complexity and pattern formation and a
broad theoretical exposure to cognitive
science social innovation political and
economic thinking and critical analysis
of historic patterns I already have
degrees in physics philosophy
mathematics and atmospheric science my
plan now is to partner with the
International Center for Earth
simulation whose mission is to dedicate
one of the world's fastest
supercomputers to the integration of
knowledge about the Earth's many coupled
systems and I am seeking additional
partnerships with research institutes
vacated to the study of cognition and
culture sustainable futures and social
innovation this will facilitate
knowledge integration across the
cognitive sciences it will allow us to
create modeling frameworks for the study
of human responses to global change as
an ongoing endeavor it will stimulate
the creation of new educational
curricula similar to the degree program
in Earth's systems environment and
society I designed for the University of
Illinois several years ago and it will
promote the formation of a new research
agenda with a cross-cutting research
center on human interface design for
global systems that brings together
leading thinkers to collaborate with one
another this is what I am setting out to
do so why am I proposing this now
because in the last 40 years there's
been an emerging picture from the
cognitive sciences that for the first
time ever tells us what real human
nature is like grounded in a philosophy
of embodiment we are beginning to see
how the mind really works as an
ecologically intertwined web of
connections between body brain and
environment foundational knowledge is
getting set in place through
evolutionary studies of hominid history
that tells us who we really are on top
of this we are beginning to see how the
mind operates research in neuroscience
is telling us how the brain works why
emotions shape human reasoning in the
ways they do and how mental abilities
develop across the lifespan research in
linguistics is showing us where language
comes from how meaning arises and why we
are such a creative animal and
psychological research is revealing
where our morality comes from and how it
feeds and plays off the various cultures
we live in so we finally have a basis
for connecting brain with culture all
the way through from synaptic firing to
cultural narratives and institutional
identities four years ago I partnered
with linguist and cognitive
scientist George Lake off to articulate
a framework for analyzing the cognitive
dimension of policy and I launched a
consulting firm to translate this
framework into useful tools for
practitioners in the policy development
in advocacy arenas let's make this more
concrete with an example Social Security
has proven to be a robustly popular
program in every country that adopts it
why is that because it's a user
interface provides a positive experience
that is intuitively appealing easy to
understand and reinforced across the
lifespan we tend to see it as a
community piggy bank where people who
work hard all their lives pay in so they
will be taken care of in their old age
they experience this by having money
garnished from their checks and they
know what to expect from the system its
popularity can be attributed to a set of
cognitive design criteria including
understandability inherent appeal and
positive reinforcement through life
experience this makes sense when we
consider the mental models cultural
values and structured life experiences
that constitute how people think about
social security efforts to design social
policy that need to last for the long
haul like those for addressing climate
change natural disasters and other
systemic challenges need to incorporate
a policy response element that is
informed by cognitive science if they
are to be adopted successfully now is
the time to formalize these foundations
at the point of coupling between
humanity and the Earth's many natural
systems as we seek to address global
change in the 21st century with
unprecedented threats of climate
disruption resource scarcity financial
shocks and more we need rigorous methods
for the study of the human dimension and
this is what i mean by viable models for
human interface design getting humans
right is essential it is the great blind
spot in all our efforts to design social
policies for our economic financial and
political institutions
by returning to the Academy I will forge
partnerships with leading scholars gain
credibility as an advanced researcher
and help build next generation academic
programs for the students of tomorrow
only a PhD will give me the long-term
credibility intellectual rigor in formal
training I'll need to complete this work
yet the world can't wait any longer for
the synthesis to get underway so I want
the PhD itself to pursue the solution i
will need allies to complete this phase
of my quest so what can you do to help
I've identified three things that will
be needed to initiate this bold research
agenda and make it a success number one
a forward-thinking research university
that supports innovative scholarship my
top choices are Oxford's Martin 21st
century school Columbia University's
Earth Institute and Stanford's Earth
System science program because they
promote multidisciplinary approaches to
addressing 21st century challenges an
excellent fit for what I proposed here
so if you know anyone of these
institutions please let me know and
perhaps pass this video along and put in
a good word for me number 2 funding
being a new field of study means it
doesn't fit well within the standard
categories for research grants I need
financial sponsorship to maintain the
intellectual flexibility that this
ambitious endeavor requires so if you
know of any vado foundations client
organizations forward-thinking
philanthropists or anyone else you might
step up and fund this please let me know
and of course number 3 collaborators
researchers social entrepreneurs and
professional strategists who share this
integrative vision and want to partner
on projects moving forward you can reach
me here to talk more I'd love to hear
your thoughts ideas and suggestions
thank you for taking the time to
consider my proposal I'm looking forward
to hearing from you